Namaste. Good morning.
ناماستي , صباح الخير
I'm very happy to be here in India.
أنا سعيدة جداً لكوني هنا في الهند
And I've been thinking a lot about what I have learned
أمضيت وقتا في التفكير كثيراً عما تعلمت
over these last particularly 11 years
خلال خبرتي في السنوات الـ11 الماضية
with V-Day and "The Vagina Monologues,"
مع حركة "V.Day" المهتمة بقضية العنف ضد المرأة , ومسرحية " مونولوجات المهبل "
traveling the world,
التي إمتدت لجميع العالم
essentially meeting with women and girls across the planet
وبالأخص لقائاتي مع النساء والفتيات عبر جميع أرجاء العالم
to stop violence against women.
لإيقاف العنف ضد النساء
What I want to talk about today
ما أريد الحديث عنه اليوم
is this particular cell,
هي تلك الخلية المحددة
or grouping of cells, that is in each and every one of us.
أو مجموعة الخلايا الموجودة بداخل كل منا
And I want to call it the girl cell.
وأريد تسميتها بالخلية الأنثوية
And it's in men as well as in women.
وهي في الرجال كما هي في النساء
I want you to imagine that this particular grouping of cells
أريدكم أن تتخيلوا أن تجمع هذه الخلايا المعينة
is central to the evolution of our species
هي مركز تطور جنسنا البشري
and the continuation of the human race.
و إستمرار جنسنا البشري
And I want you imagine that at some point in history
وأريدكم أن تتخيلوا أنه في نقطة معينة من التاريخ
a group of powerful people invested in owning and controlling the world
إستثمر مجموعة من الناس الأقوياء في تمْلك العالم و التحكم به
understood that the suppression of this particular cell,
وعلموا أن قمع هذه الخلية بعينها
the oppression of these cells,
وإضطهادها
the reinterpretation of these cells,
وإعادة تشكيلها
the undermining of these cells,
وتقويضها
getting us to believe in the weakness of these cells
جعلنا نؤمن بضعف هذه الخلايا الأنثوية
and the crushing, eradicating, destroying,
وأن سحقها , والقضاء عليها , وتدميرها
reducing these cells,
والتقليل من حجم هذه الخلايا
basically began the process of killing off the girl cell,
يبدأ بعملية القضاء على الخلية الانثوية
which was, by the way, patriarchy.
عن طريق سلطة الرجال
I want you to imagine that the girl is a chip
أريدكم أن تتخيلوا أن الفتاة هي الرقاقة
in the huge macrocosm of collective consciousness.
في محيط عالمنا الكبير الذي يحمل وعيًا جماعيًا
And it is essential to balance, to wisdom
وهي مهمة في تحقيق التوازن , والحكمة
and to actually the future of all of us.
وكذلك تحقيق المستقبل لنا جميعا
And then I want you to imagine that this girl cell
وبعد ذلك أريد منكم تصور أن الخلية الأنثوية
is compassion,
هي الرحمة
and it's empathy, and it's passion itself,
إنها التعاطف , إنها العاطفة بحد ذاتها
and it's vulnerability,
إنها الحساسية
and it's openness, and it's intensity,
إنها الرحابة , إنها الإنفعال
and it's association, and it's relationship,
إنها الترابط , إنها العلاقة
and it is intuitive.
إنها الحدسية
And then let's think how compassion informs wisdom,
ودعونا نفكر كيف أن الرحمة تعلم الحكمة
and that vulnerability is our greatest strength,
وأن الحساسية هي أعظم قوة لنا
and that emotions have inherent logic,
وأن تلك المشاعر لها منطق موروث
which lead to radical, appropriate, saving action.
التي تقود إلى الراديكالية ( السعي للتجديد ) , والملائمة , وتجنب الأفعال
And then let's remember that we've been taught
وبعد ذلك دعونا نتذكر أننا كلنا قد تعلمنا
the exact opposite by the powers that be,
عكس ذلك من الذين يملكون السلطة حيث علمونا
that compassion clouds your thinking,
أن الرحمة تغّيم تفكيرنا
that it gets in the way,
أنها تقف في الطريق
that vulnerability is weakness,
أن الحساسية تعني ضعف
that emotions are not to be trusted,
تلك المشاعر لا يمكن الوثوق بها
and you're not supposed to take things personally,
وأنك لا يفترض أن تأخذ الأمور على نحو شخصي
which is one of my favorites.
التي تعد من أفضل صفاتي
I think the whole world has essentially
أعتقد أن العالم بأكمله
been brought up not to be a girl.
قد تربي أساسًا على ألا يكون فتاه
How do we bring up boys? What does it mean to be a boy?
كيف نربي أولادنا ؟ ماذا يعني أن تكون ولدًا ؟
To be a boy really means not to be a girl.
إن حقيقة أن تكون ولدًا هو ألا تكون فتاة
To be a man means not to be a girl.
لكي تصبح رجلًا يعني ألا تكون فتاة
To be a woman means not to be a girl.
لكي تصبحي إمرأة يعني ألا تكوني فتاة
To be strong means not to be a girl.
لكي تصبح قوي يعني ألا تكون فتاة
To be a leader means not to be a girl.
لكي تكون قائد يعني ألا تكون فتاة
I actually think that
في الحقيقة أنا أعتقد
being a girl is so powerful
أن تكون فتاة يعني أن تكون في غاية القوة
that we've had to train everyone not to be that.
لدرجة أننا دربنا الجميع على أن لا يصبحوا كذلك
(Laughter)
( تصفيق )
And I'd also like to say that the irony
وأود أن أقول أن المفارقة هنا
of course, is that denying girl,
هو بالطبع أن إنكار فتاة
suppressing girl, suppressing emotion,
وقمعها , وإضطهاد المشاعر
refusing feeling has lead thus here.
و رفضها أدى بنا بالتالي إلى هذا الحال
Where we have now come to live in a world where
حيث أصبحنا اليوم نعيش في عالم
the most extreme forms of violence,
به أكثر صور العنف تطرفًا
the most horrific poverty,
وأكثر صور الفقر إدقاعًا
genocide, mass rapes,
والإبادة الجماعية , و الإغتصاب الجماعي
the destruction of the Earth, is completely out of control.
و تدمير الأرض , إن كل ذلك حتما خارج السيطرة
And because we have suppressed our girl cells
ولأننا قمعنا الخلايا الأنثوية بداخلنا
and suppressed our girl-ship,
و نفينا إنتمائنا الداخلي للفتيات
we do not feel what is going on.
فإننا لا نشعر بما يجري حولنا
So, we are not being charged with
لذلك , نحن لا يلقى اللوم علينا
the adequate response to what is happening.
بسبب عدم إستجابتنا الكافية للأحداث من حولنا
I want to talk a little bit about
أريد التحدث قليلًا
the Democratic Republic of Congo.
عن جمهورية الكونغو الديموقراطية
For me, it was the turning point of my life.
شخصيًا كانت تلك هي نقطة التحول في حياتي
I have spent a lot of time there in the last three years.
أمضيت الكثير من الوقت هناك في الثلاثة أعوام الماضية
I feel up to that point I had seen a lot in the world,
إلى حد جعلني أؤمن بأني رأيت ما يكفي في هذا العالم
a lot of violence.
الكثير من العنف
I essentially lived in the rape mines of the world for the last 12 years.
لم تكن حوادث الإغتصاب أمرًا غريبًا عني فقد عشت 12 سنة وسط هذه القضايا
But the Democratic Republic of Congo
ولكن الكونغو
really was the turning point in my soul.
كانت حقيقة نقطة التحول في روحي
I went and I spent time
قضيت الوقت
in a place called Bukavu
في مكان يدعي (بوكوفا)
in a hospital called the Panzi Hospital,
بالتحديد في مستشفي يسمي (بانزي)
with a doctor who was as close to a saint as any person I've ever met.
مع دكتور كاد أن يكون قديسًا بالمقارنة مع أي شخص آخر قابلته في حياتي
His name is Dr. Denis Mukwege.
إسمه ( د.دينيس موكيجي)
In the Congo, for those of you who don't know,
وفي الكونغو للذين لا يعرفون منكم
there has been a war raging for the last 12 years,
كانت هناك حرب تصاعدت على مدى الـ12 سنة الأخيرة
a war that has killed nearly six million people.
إنها حرب قتلت حوالي 6 مليون نسمة
It is estimated that somewhere between 300,000 and 500,000 women
قدرت بأن حول 300,000 و 500,000 إمرأة
have been raped there.
تعرضوا للإغتصاب هناك
When I spent my first weeks at Panzi hospital
عندما قضيت أول أسابيع لي في مستشفي (بانزي)
I sat with women
جالست نساء
who sat and lined up every day to tell me their stories.
اللاتي إصطففن وجلسن معي يوميًا ليحدثنني عن قصصهن
Their stories were so horrific,
وقصصهن كانت مأساوية جدًا
and so mind-blowing and so on the other side of human existence,
ومفجعة للغاية , وكذلك لا تصدق أنها تصدر من الوجود البشري
that to be perfectly honest with you, I was shattered.
صدقًا , كنت قد تحطمت
And I will tell you that what happened
وسأسرد عليكم ما حدث
is through that shattering,
في خلال ذلك التحطم
listening to the stories of eight-year-old girls who had their insides eviscerated,
حيث إستمعت إلى قصص لفتيات في الثامنة من عمرهن إنتزعت أحشائهن
who had guns and bayonets and things shoved inside them
وحشرت مسدسات, وحربات , وأشياء أخرى في باطنهن
so they had holes, literally, inside them
لذا كانت لديهن ثقوب وأعني حرفيًا ...ثقوبٌ في داخلهن
where their pee and poop came out of them.
حيث تخرج الفضلات من تلك الثقوب ..
Listening to the story of 80-year-old women
و بالإستماع إلى قصة نساء في الـ80 من عمرهن
who were tied to chains and circled,
الذين قيدوهن بالسلاسل و طوقوهن
and where groups of men would come and rape them periodically,
ثم يأتي مجموعة من الرجال ليغتصبوهن بصفة دورية
all in the name of economic exploitation
وكل ذلك تحت ظلال الإستغلال الإقتصادي
to steal the minerals so the West can have it and profit from them.
لسرقة الثروات الطبيعية ويبيعوها للغرب ليربح منها
My mind was so shattered.
كان عقلي حقًا يمر بحالة إرهاقٍ عصبي
But what happened for me is that that shattering
ولكن ما حدث فعلا هو أن الإرهاق العصبي
actually emboldened me
جعلني شجاعة
in a way I have never been emboldened.
بطريقة لم تحدث لي نهائيا من قبل
That shattering, that opening of my girl cell,
ذلك التحطم , ذلك الإنفتاح على خليتي الأنثوية
that kind of massive breakthrough of my heart
ذلك النوع من الإكتشاف الهائل لقلبي
allowed me to become more courageous, and braver,
سمح لي أن أصبح أكثر جرأة وشجاعة
and actually more clever
و في الحقيقة أكثر ذكاء
than I had been in the past in my life.
مما كنت عليه في ماضي حياتي
I want to say that I think the powers that be
وأريد أن أقول أني أعتقد أن أصحاب السلطات
know that empire-building
الذين يعلمون أن بناء إمبراطورية
is actually -- that feelings get in the way of empire-building.
هو عبارة عن المشاعر التي تقف في طريق بنائها
Feelings get in the way of the mass acquisition of the Earth,
المشاعر التي تقف في طريق إحتلال الكرة الأرضية
and excavating the Earth, and destroying things.
وحفر الأرض , وتدمير الأشياء
I remember, for example, when my father,
أتذكر مثلا عندما كان والدي
who was very, very violent, used to beat me.
في غاية العنف , كان يعتاد ضربي
And he would actually say, while he was beating me,
وكان يقول بينما يضربني
"Don't you cry. Don't you dare cry."
" لا تبكي , إياكِ أن تتجرأي على البكاء "
Because my crying somehow exposed his brutality to him.
لأن بكائي كان بطريقة ما يُعري وحشيته أمامه
And even in the moment he didn't want to be reminded
وحتي في لحظة وحشيته لم يرد
of what he was doing.
أن يذكره أحد بوحشيته أو بما يفعله
I know that we have systematically annihilated the girl cell.
اعلم بإننا إنتهجنا إبادة الخلية الأنثوية
And I want to say we've annihilated it in men as well as in women.
وأريد أن أقول أننا قد محوناها في الرجال كما هو الحال في النساء
And I think in some ways
وأعتقد في بعض الأحيان
we've been much harsher to men
أننا قسونا أكثر على الرجال
in the annihilation of their girl cell.
في محو الخلية الأنثوية بداخلهم
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
I see how boys have been brought up, and I see this across the planet:
أرى كيفية تربية الأولاد حول العالم
to be tough, to be hardened,
ليكونوا صارمين , و أشداء
to distance themselves from their tenderness, to not cry.
و أن ينأوا بأنفسهم عن الحنان, وألا يبكوا
I actually realized once in Kosovo,
في الحقيقة أدركت ذلك مرة في كوسوفو
when I watched a man break down,
عنما رأيت رجل يفقد أعصابه
that bullets are actually hardened tears,
وأن الرصاصات بالفعل تحجر الدموع
that when we don't allow men to have their girl self
وأننا عندما لا نسمح للرجال بأن يجدوا الأنثى بداخلهم
and have their vulnerability, and have their compassion,
وألا يكون لديهم جانبهم الحساس , و لا جانبهم الرحوم
and have their hearts, that they become hardened and hurtful
وألا يكون لديهم قلب , عندها يصبحون قاسين ,و مؤذين
and violent.
وعنيفين
And I think we have taught men to be secure
وأنا أظن بأننا قد علمنا الرجال أن يشعروا بالأمان
when they are insecure,
عندما لا يشعرون كذلك !
to pretend they know things when they don't know things,
وأن يتظاهروا بأنهم يعلمون أمور لا يعلمونها حقًا
or why would we be where we are?
وإلا لماذا نحن على ما عليه اليوم؟
To pretend they're not a mess when they are a mess.
إنهم يتظاهرون أنهم ليسوا في فوضى بينما هم فيها ..
And I will tell you a very funny story.
وسأخبركم بقصة مضحكة
On my way here on the airplane, I was walking up and down the aisle of the plane.
في طريقى إلى هنا على الطائرة , كنت أسير فى ممر الطائرة
And all these men, literally at least 10 men,
وكل الرجال هناك , وبصدق كانوا على الأقل 10 رجال
were in their little seats watching chick flicks.
فى مقاعدهم يشاهدون أفلام نسائية (مليئة بالمشاعر وموجهة لهن)
And they were all alone, and I thought, "This is the secret life of men."
كانوا جميعا لوحدهم , وجال بخاطري " هذه حياة الرجال السرية"
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
I've traveled, as I said,
كما قلت مسبقاً , لقد سافرت كثيراً
to many, many countries,
لدول عديدة
and I've seen, if we do what we do to the girl inside us
ولقد رأيت , أننا اذا فعلنا ما نفعله للخلية الأنثوية بداخلنا
then obviously it's horrific to think
فعندها من الواضح أنه سيصبح من المروع التفكير
what we do to girls in the world.
في ما سوف نفعله للفتيات حول العالم
And we heard from Sunitha yesterday,
وقد سمعنا أمس من المحاضرة (سونيثا)
and Kavita about what we do to girls.
والمحاضرة (كافيتا) عما نفعله للفتيات
But I just want to say that
ولكننى أريد القول
I've met girls with knife wounds and cigarette burns,
إني قد قابلت فتيات بهن جروح أثر سكاكين ,وأثار حرق بسبب السجائر
who are literally being treated like ashtrays.
اللاتي قد عُوملون تماما مثل مطفئات السجائر
I've seen girls be treated like garbage cans.
رأيت فتيات تلقوا معاملة مثل صناديق القمامة
I've seen girls who were beaten by their mothers
و رأيت فتيات ضربتهن أمهاتهن
and brothers and fathers and uncles.
وأخوتهن , وآبائهن , وأعمامهن
I've seen girls starving themselves to death in America
و رأيت فتيات يتضورون جوعاً حتى الموت في أمريكا
in institutions to look like some idealized version of themselves.
لهدف أن يظهروا في صورة مثالية لأنفسهن
I've seen that we cut girls and we control them
و رأيت أننا نختن الفتيات و نتحكم بهن
and we keep them illiterate,
ونبقيهم أميين
or we make them feel bad about being too smart.
أو نجعلهن يشعرن بالسوء في كونهن ذكيات
We silence them. We make them feel guilty
نكمم أصواتهن , ونجعلهن يشعرن بالذنب
for being smart. We get them to behave,
لكونهن ذكيات , و جعلناهن يتصرفن بطريقة معينة
to tone it down, not to be too intense.
ليخفضوا أصواتهن , وألا يكنّ إنفعاليات جدًا
We sell them, we kill them as embryos,
نبيعهن , ونقتلهن مثل الأجنة
we enslave them, we rape them.
و نستعبدهن...و نغتصبهن
We are so accustomed to robbing girls
إعتدنا سرقة الفتيات
of the subject of being the subjects of their lives
لغرض أن نكون أهداف حياتهن
that we have now actually objectified them
لدرجة أننا بالفعل جعلناهن سلعة
and turned them into commodities.
و حولناهن إلى بضائع تباع وتُشترى
The selling of girls is rampant across the planet.
إن بيع الفتيات منتشر حول العالم
And in many places they are worth less than goats and cows.
و فى أماكن كثيرة يعد ثمنهن أقل من الماعز ,أو البقر
But I also want to talk about the fact that
لكننى أيضاً أريد أن أتحدث عن حقيقة أن
if one in eight people on the planet
اذا كانت نسبة 1 إلى 8 على الأرض
are girls between the ages of 10 to 24,
هم فتيات تتراوح أعمارهن بين 10 و 24
they are they key, really, in the developing world,
فإنهم بالفعل الأساس في نمو العالم
as well as in the whole world, to the future of humanity.
كما هو الحال فى باقى أنحاء العالم و لمستقبل الإنسانية
And if girls are in trouble because they face systematic disadvantages
وإذا كانوا الفتيات فى معاناه بسبب مواجهتهن لعيوب منهجية
that keep them where society wants them to be,
في جعلهن فى مكان حيث يريدهم المجتمع به
including lack of access to healthcare,
بما فى ذلك القصور عن الرعاية الصحية
education, healthy foods,
و التعليم , الطعام الصحى
labor force participation.
و المشاركة في ميدان العمل
The burden of all the household tasks
و عبء كل المهام المنزلية
usually falls on girls and younger siblings,
يقع في العادة على الفتيات وأصغر الأخوات
which ensures that they will never overcome these barriers.
للتأكد من أنهم لن يتغلبوا على هذه الحواجز أبداً
The state of girls, the condition of girls,
إن حاله الفتيات , ووضعهن
will, in my belief -- and that's the girl inside us
وأن الفتاة بداخلنا
and the girl in the world -- determine whether
والفتاة فى العالم ,سوف تحدد
the species survives.
بقاء الجنس البشري من عدم بقائه.
And what I want to suggest is that,
وما أريد إقتراحه
having talked to girls, because I just finished a new book called
بعد أن تحدثت مع فتيات , لأننى قد إنتهيت من كتاب جديد يسمى
"I Am an Emotional Creature: The Secret Life of Girls Around the World,"
" أنا كائنة عاطفية : الحياة السرية للفتيات حول العالم "
I've been talking to girls for five years,
كما قلت تحدثت مع فتيات على مر 5 سنوات
and one of the things that I've seen is true everywhere
وأحد الأشياء التى رأيتها بالفعل حقيقية فى كل مكان
is that the verb that's been enforced on girl
هو أن الكلمة التي تُطعم للفتيات
is the verb "to please."
هو كلمة ( الإرضاء )
Girls are trained to please.
تدربوا الفتيات على الإرضاء
I want to change the verb.
أريد أن أغير هذه الكلمة
I want us all to change the verb.
أريد من الجميع تغير هذه الكلمة
I want the verb to be "educate,"
أريدها أن تكون ( التعليم )
or "activate," or "engage,"
أو (التفعيل) , أو (الإنخراط)
or "confront," or "defy," or "create."
أو ( المواجهة) , أو (التحدي) , أو ( الإنتاج)
If we teach girls to change the verb
إذا علمنا الفتيات على تغير تلك الكلمة
we will actually enforce the girl inside us
بذلك سوف نظهر الفتاة بداخلنا جميعاً
and the girl inside them.
والفتاة بداخلهم أيضا
And I have to now share a few stories
والآن لدي بعض القصص التي أود أن أشارككم بها
of girls I've seen across the planet
لفتيات قابلتهن ورأيتهن عبر العالم
who have engaged their girl,
الذين إتحدوا بالخلايا الأنثوية بداخلهن
who have taken on their girl in spite of
الذين إعتنقوا الفتاة بداخلهن
all the circumstances around them.
بالرغم من كل الظروف حولهن
I know a 14-year-old girl in the Netherlands,
أعرف فتاه بعمر 14 عاماً في هولندا
for example, who is demanding that she take a boat
على سبيل المثال , والتي تطالب بأن تبحر بقارب
and go around the entire world by herself.
لتأخذ جولة حول العالم بنفسها
There is a teenage girl who just recently
هناك مراهقة صغيرة التي خرجت قبل فترة
went out and knew that she needed 56 stars
وعلمت أنها بحاجة إلى 56 نجمة
tattooed on the right side of her face.
لتوشم على جانب وجهها الأيمن
There is a girl, Julia Butterfly Hill,
و هناك فتاه تسمى (جوليا بترفلاي هيل)
who lived for a year in a tree
عاشت عاماً كاملاً على شجرة
because she wanted to protect the wild oaks.
لأنها أرادت أن تحمى السنديان البرية
There is a girl who I met 14 years ago in Afghanistan
و هناك فتاه قابلتها فى أفغانستان منذ 14 عاماً مضت
who I have adopted as my daughter
التى تبنيتها كإبنه لي
because her mother was killed. Her mother was a revolutionary.
لأن أمها قد قُتلت حيث كانت والدتها ثوريه
And this girl, when she was 17 years old,
وهذه الفتاه , عندما أصبحت في 17 من عمرها
wore a burqa in Afghanistan,
لبست البرقع فى أفغانستان
and went into the stadiums
وذهبت إلى ميدان الحدث
and documented the atrocities that were going on towards women,
ووثقت ما تعاني منه النساء من الأعمال الوحشية تجاههن
underneath her burqa, with a video.
وهي مرتدية البرقع و موثقة ذلك بالفيديو
And that video became the video that went out all over the world
وذلك الفيديو أصبح منتشرًا حول العالم
after 9/11 to show what was going on in Afghanistan.
بعد أحداث 11 من سبتمبر, ليُظهر ماذا كان يحدث بالفعل فى أفغانستان .
I want to talk about Rachel Corrie
أريد أن أتحدث عن (ريتشل كوري)
who was in her teens when she stood in front of an Israeli tank
التي كانت يافعة عندما وقفت أمام دبابة إسرائيلية
to say, "End the occupation."
لتقول " أوقفوا الإحتلال "
And she knew she risked death and she was literally gunned down
وعرفت أنها خاطرت للموت, والتي رميت بالفعل بالرصاص
and rolled over by that tank.
ودهستها الدبابة الحربية ..
And I want to talk about a girl that I just met recently
وأريد أن أتحدث عن فتاة قابلتها حديثاً
in Bukavu, who was impregnated by her rapist.
في بوكوفا , التي حملت من مغتصبها
And she was holding her baby.
وكانت تضم طفلها في حضنها
And I asked her if she loved her baby.
وسألتها إذا كانت تحب طفلها
And she looked into her baby's eyes and she said,
ونظرت إلى عينى طفلها قائلة
"Of course I love my baby. How could I not love my baby?
" بالطبع أحب طفلي , كيف لي ألا أحب طفلي ؟
It's my baby and it's full of love."
إنه طفلي , المشبع بالحب "
The capacity for girls to overcome situations
إن قدرة الفتيات على تعدى المواقف
and to move on levels, to me, is mind-blowing.
بأشواط كبيرة , بالنسبة لي ذلك أمر مدهش
There is a girl named Dorcas, and I just met her in Kenya.
وهناك فتاه إسمها (دوركاس) , قابلتها في كينيا
Dorcas is 15 years old,
تبلغ (دوركاس) 15 من عمرها
and she was trained in self-defense.
وتدربت على الدفاع عن النفس
A few months ago she was picked up on the street
ومنذ شهور قريبة إختطفوها من الشارع
by three older men.
كانوا 3 رجال كبار في السن
They kidnapped her, they put her in a car.
قد إختطفوها , ووضعوها في سيارة
And through her self-defense, she grabbed their Adam's apples,
وبدفاعها عن نفسها شلت حركتهم بضرب (تفاحة آدم) حنجرتهم
she punched them in the eyes
وبلكمهم على أعينهم
and she got herself free and out of the car.
وحررت نفسها منهم وخرجت من السيارة
In Kenya, in August,
و فى كينيا , في شهر أغسطس
I went to visit one of the V-Day safe houses for girls,
ذهبت لزيارة أحد الديار الرعاية لحركة "V.Day" للفتيات
a house we opened seven years ago
إنه دار إفتتحناه منذ سبعة أعوام
with an amazing woman named Agnes Pareyio.
مع إمرأة رائعة إسمها (أجنيس بريو)
Agnes was a woman who was cut when she was a little girl,
(أجنيس) كانت إمرأة ختنت عندما كانت فتاه صغيرة
she was female genitally mutilated.
كانت أنثى شُوهت أعضائها التناسلية
And she made a decision as many women do across this planet,
وقد أخذت قرار مثل كثير من النساء حول العالم
that what was done to her would not be enforced and done
أن ما حدث لها لن يحدث
to other women and girls.
لنساء وفتيات أخريات
So, for years Agnes walked through the Rift valley.
لذا , عبرت ( أجنيس) وادي ريفت لسنوات
She taught girls what a healthy vagina looked like,
لتعلم الفتيات كيف يبدو شكل العضو التناسلي السليم
and what a mutilated vagina looked like.
وكيف تبدو الأعضاء التناسلية المشوهه
And in that time she saved many girls. And when we met her
وفي ذلك الوقت كانت قد أنقذت فتيات كثيرات , وعندما قابلناها
we asked her what we could do for her,
سألناها ماذا نستطيع تقديمه لها
and she said, "Well, if you got me a Jeep I could get around a lot faster."
وقالت : " حسناً , لو أعطيتونى سيارة جيب سوف يساعدني ذلك على التنقل بصورة أسرع."
So, we got her a Jeep. And then she saved 4,500 girls.
لذا , أعطيناها سيارة جيب , وبعدها أنقذت 4,500 فتاه
And then we asked her, "Okay, what else do you need?"
وبعدها سألناها : " حسنا , أهناك شيء آخر تحتاجينه ؟ "
And she said, "Well, now, I need a house."
وأجابت : " الآن , أحتاج إلى منزل "
So, seven years ago Agnes built the first V-Day safe house
لذلك , منذ 7 سنوات أقامت (أنجيس) أول دار رعاية لحركة "V.Day" للفتيات
in Narok, Kenya, in the Masai land.
فى نوركا , وكينيا ,و فى أرض الماسايا
And it was a house where girls could run away,
وكانت هذا الدار لرعاية الفتيات حيث يستطعن اللجوء إليها
they could save their clitoris, they wouldn't be cut,
وأستطاعوا إنقاذ أعضائهن التناسية من الختان
they could go to school.
والذهاب إلى المدرسة
And in the years that Agnes has had the house,
وفي السنوات التي حصلت فيها (أجنيس) على الدار
she has changed the situation there.
إستطاعت أن تغير الحال هناك
She has literally become deputy mayor.
أصبحت نائبة حاكم المنطقة
She's changed the rules.
و غيرت القوانين
The whole community has bought in to what she's doing.
و إنصاع المجتمع بأكمله لما تفعله
When we were there she was doing a ritual
عندما كنا هناك كانت تقوم بنوع من الطقس
where she reconciles girls, who have run away, with their families.
حيث كانت تجمع الفتيات بأسرهن الذين هربوا منهم
And there was a young girl named Jaclyn.
وكانت هناك فتاه صغيرة إسمها (جاكلين)
Jaclyn was 14 years old and she was in her Masai family
(جاكلين) كانت تبلغ من العمر 14 عاماً , وكانت تعيش بين أسرتها الماسية ( قبيلة فى كينيا )
and there's a drought in Kenya.
وكان هناك جفاف فى كينيا
So cows are dying, and cows are the most
ولذلك كانت الأبقار تموت , وهناك تعد الأبقار قيمة
valued possession.
ومن أكثر الممتلكات قيمة
And Jaclyn overheard her father
وسمعت (جاكلين) والدها بالصدفة
talking to an old man about
يتحدث مع رجل عجوز
how he was about to sell her for the cows.
على أنه على وشك أن يبيعها مقابل البقر
And she knew that meant she would be cut.
وعلمت أن ذلك يعني ختانها
She knew that meant she wouldn't go to school.
و عرفت أن معنى ذلك أنها لن تتمكن من الذهاب إلى المدرسة
She knew that meant she wouldn't have a future.
ولن يكون لها مستقبل
She knew she would have to marry that old man, and she was 14.
وأنها سترغم على الزواج بذلك الرجل الكبير و هي تبلغ من العمر 14 سنة
So, one afternoon, she'd heard about the safe house,
لذا بعد ظهر أحد الأيام كانت قد سمعت عن دار الرعاية
Jaclyn left her father's house
تركت (جاكلين) منزل والدها
and she walked for two days, two days
وذهبت سيراً على الأقدام على مدى يومين
through Masai land.
خلال أرض الماسايا
She slept with the hyenas. She hid at night.
لقد نامت مع الضباع , و إختبأت فى الليل
She imagined her father killing her on one hand,
تخيلت والدها يقتلها بيد واحدة
and Mama Agnes greeting her,
و أن ماما ( أجنيس) كانت تحييها
with the hope that she would greet her when she got to the house.
بأمل أنها سوف تحييها عندما تصل إلى الدار
And when she got to the house she was greeted.
وعندما وصلت إلى الدار إستُقبلت بتحيه
Agnes took her in, and Agnes loved her,
وقبلت بها (أجنيس) وأحبتها
and Agnes supported her for the year.
ودعمتها (أجنيس) طوال السنة
She went to school and she found her voice,
وذهبت إلى المدرسة , ووجدت صوتها
and she found her identity, and she found her heart.
وهويتها , و قلبها
Then, her time was ready
وعندئذ , حان وقتها
when she had to go back to talk to her father
عندما كان لابد لها أن تعود لتتحدث مع والدها
about the reconciliation, after a year.
بخصوص المصالحة بعد مرور عام
I had the privilege of being in the hut
وكان لى شرف الإمتياز أن أكون فى الموقف
when she was reunited with her father and reconciled.
عندما تصالحت مع والدها وأصبحوا متحدين مرة آخرى
In that hut, we walked in,
وفى ذلك الموقف , دخلنا الغرفة
and her father and his four wives were sitting there,
ووالدها وزوجاته الأربعة كانوا جالسين هناك
and her sisters who had just returned because
وإخواتها الفتيات قد رجعوا إلى المنزل
they had all fled when she had fled,
لأنهم جميعا هربوا عندما هربت هي
and her primary mother, who had been beaten
وأما أمها التي إعتنت بها , التى تعرضت للضرب
in standing up for her with the elders.
بسبب دفاعها عنها مع شيوخ القبيلة
When her father saw her and saw who she had become,
وعندما رأها والدها , ورأى ما أصبحت عليه
in her full girl self,
كفتاه كبيرة و يافعة
he threw his arms around her and broke down crying.
طوقها بذراعيه وإنهار بكاءً
He said, "You are beautiful. You have grown into a gorgeous woman.
وقال لها : " أنتِ جميلة , لقد كبرتِ وأصبحت إمرأة رائعة"
We will not cut you.
لن نختنكِ
And I give you my word, here and now,
وأعدك بذلك هنا الآن ..
that we will not cut your sisters either."
ولن نختن إخوتك الفتيات أيضا "
And what she said to him was,
وقالت له :
"You were willing to sell me for four cows,
" كنتم تنوون أن تبيعونى مقابل أربع بقرات
and a calf and some blankets.
وعجل , وبعض البطانيات
But I promise you, now that I will be educated
و لكنى أعدكم , الآن لأني سوف أصبح متعلمة
I will always take care of you,
فإني سوف أرعاكم دومًا
and I will come back and I will build you a house.
وسوف أعود وأبنى لكم منزلًا
And I will be in your corner for the rest of your life."
وسأكون فى صفكم طوال حياتكم . "
For me, that is the power of girls.
بالنسبة لي , هذه هى قوة الفتيات
And that is the power of transformation.
وهذه هى فائدة التحول للأفضل
I want to close today
أريد أن أختتم اليوم
with a new piece from my book.
بجزء جديد من كتابى
And I want to do it tonight
وأريد أن أقرئه اليوم
for the girl in everybody here.
من أجل الفتاه التى بداخل كل منا هنا
And I want to do it for Sunitha.
وأريد أن أفعل ذلك من أجل (سونيثا)
And I want to do it for the girls that Sunitha talked about yesterday,
وأيضاً من أجل الفتيات التى تحدثت عنهم (سونيثا) بالأمس
the girls who survive, the girls who can become somebody else.
الذين نجوا , والذين يستطيعون أن يصبحوا شخص آخر
But I really want to do it for each and every person here,
ولكننى بالفعل أريد أن أفعل ذلك من أجل كل شخص هنا
to value the girl in us,
لتقدير الفتاة بداخلنا
to value the part that cries,
لتقدير الجزء الباكي
to value the part that's emotional,
لتقدير الجزء الشاعري
to value the part that's vulnerable,
لتقدير الجزء الحساس
to understand that's where the future lies.
لفهم أين يكمن المستقبل
This is called "I'm An Emotional Creature."
يدعى الكتاب " أنا كائنة عاطفية"
And it happened because I met a girl in Watts, L.A.
وكتبته لأننى قابلت فتاه فى مدينة واتس بـ (لوس أنجلوس)
I was asking girls if they like being a girl,
كنت أسأل الفتيات إذا كان يعجبهم كونهم فتيات
and all the girls were like, "No, I hate it. I can't stand it.
و كان ردهم جميعا مثل : " لا , أنا أكره ذلك , أنا لا أستطيع تحمل ذلك
It's all bad. My brothers get everything."
من السيء أن إخوتى الأولاد يحصلون على كل شيئ ."
And this girl just sat up and went, "I love being a girl.
ووقفت واحدة فقط منهم وقالت : " أنا أُحب كونى فتاه
I'm an emotional creature!"
أنا كائنة عاطفية "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
This is for her:
هذا ما كتبته لها
I love being a girl.
أنا أحب كونى فتاه
I can feel what you're feeling
أستطيع الإحساس بما تحسه
as you're feeling inside the feeling before.
وكأني أحسست بذلك الشعور من قبل
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
Things do not come to me as intellectual theories
لا تستحضرني الأشياء كنظريات فكرية
or hard-pressed ideas.
أو كأفكار ناتجة عن ظغط شديد
They pulse through my organs and legs and burn up my ears.
إنها تنبض بداخل أعضائي , ورجليّ , وتحرق مسمعي
Oh, I know when your girlfriend's really pissed off,
آوه , أعلم عندما تغضب فعلا حبيبتك
even though she appears to give you what you want.
رغم أنها تبدو وكأنها تعطيك ما تريد
I know when a storm is coming.
أنا أعرف متى ستهب العاصفة
I can feel the invisible stirrings in the air.
أستطيع أن أحس بالإثارة المخفية في الهواء
I can tell you he won't call back. It's a vibe I share.
أستطيع أن أخبرك أنه لن يعاود الإتصال بك , إنها ذبذبات تصلني و أشاركها
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
I love that I do not take things lightly.
أنا أحب فيني أني لا أتقبل الأمور بروية
Everything is intense to me,
كل شيئ بالنسبة لي إنفعالي
the way I walk in the street, the way my momma wakes me up,
كالطريقة التى أسير بها فى الشارع ,و كالطريقة التى توقظنى بها أمى
the way it's unbearable when I lose, the way I hear bad news.
الطريقة التى لاأحتملها عند الإحساس بالفقدان , والطريقة التى أتقبل بها الأخبار السيئة
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
I am connected to everything and everyone. I was born like that.
أنا متصلة بكل شيئ , وبكل شخص ..هكذا ولدت
Don't you say all negative
لا تقل أن كل ذلك سلبي
that it's only only a teenage thing,
أن ذلك هو إحساس المراهقين
or it's only because I'm a girl.
وأن ذلك فقط لأني فتاة
These feelings make me better.
تلك المشاعر تجعلنى أفضل
They make me present. They make me ready. They make me strong.
تجعل لي وجود.. تجعلنى مستعدة.. تجعلنى قوية
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
There is a particular way of knowing.
هناك طريقة خاصة للمعرفة
It's like the older women somehow forgot.
إنها تشبه المرأة المسنة عندما تنسى في بعض الأحيان
I rejoice that it's still in my body.
أنا سعيدة إنها مازالت بداخل جسدي
Oh, I know when the coconut's about to fall.
أعلم عندما توشك جوزة الهند على السقوط
I know we have pushed the Earth too far.
أعلم أننا دفعنا الأرض لأقصى حد
I know my father isn't coming back,
أعلم أن والدي لن يعود
and that no one's prepared for the fire.
وأن لا يوجد من هو مستعد للحريق
I know that lipstick means more than show,
وأعلم أن أحمر الشفاه يعني أكثر مما يظهر
and boys are super insecure,
وأن الفتيان لا يشعرون أبدًا بالأمان
and so-called terrorists are made, not born.
وأن من يُدعون بالإرهابيين قد صُنعوا , ولم يولدوا كذلك
I know that one kiss
أعرف أن قبلة واحدة
could take away all my decision-making ability.
تستطيع إلغاء كل قدرتى على إتخاذ القرار
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
And you know what? Sometimes it should.
أوتعرفون ؟ أحياناً لابد من ذلك..
This is not extreme. It's a girl thing,
هذا ليس تطرفًا , إنه شيئ أُنثوى
what we would all be if the big door inside us flew open.
ماذا سنصبح كلنا إذا فُتح الباب الكبير بداخلنا
Don't tell me not to cry, to calm it down,
لا تخبرنى أن لا أبكى , وأن أهدأ من روعي
not to be so extreme, to be reasonable.
و ألا أسهب فى مشاعري, و أن أكون منطقية
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
It's how the earth got made, how the wind continues to pollinate.
بذلك خلقت الأرض , وأستمرت الرياح على حمل اللقاح
You don't tell the Atlantic Ocean to behave.
لا يمكنك أن تخبر المحيط الأطلسي كيف يتصرف !
I am an emotional creature.
أنا كائنة عاطفية
Why would you want to shut me down or turn me off?
لماذا تريد أن تُخرسنى أو توقفني؟
I am your remaining memory.
أنا الباقي من ذاكرتك
I can take you back.
أستطيع أن أرجعك لما كنت عليه
Nothing's been diluted.
لم تضعف مشاعرك بعد ..
Nothing's leaked out.
لم تتسرب إلى الخارج بعد ..
I love, hear me, I love
أنا أحب , إسمعوني , أنا أحب
that I can feel the feelings inside you,
أحب أني أستطيع الإحساس بما تحسه بداخلك
even if they stop my life,
حتى لو أوقفوا حياتي
even if they break my heart,
حتى لو حطموا قلبي
even if they take me off track,
حتى إذا أخرجونى من مسلكي
they make me responsible.
جعلوني عقلانية
I am an emotional, I am an emotional,
أنا عاطفية ... انا عاطفية
incondotional, devotional creature.
كائنة متفانية , و محبة بغير شروط
And I love, hear me,
و أحب ...إسمعوني ..
I love, love, love being a girl.
أنا أحب .. أحب.. أحب كوني فتاه
Can you say it with me?
هلاّ رددتوها معي؟
I love, I love, love, love
أنا أحب .. أحب .. أحب .. أحب
being a girl!
كونى فتاه !
Thank you very much.
أشكركم كثيراً
(Applause)
( تصفيق )